听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我们现在已经学习了两将军问题和拜占庭将军问题
We've now seen the two generals problem and the Byzantine generals problem.
在两将军问题中
In the two generals problem,
我们假定节点是诚实的 但消息可能会丢失
we assume that nodes are honest, but messages might get lost.
在拜占庭将军问题中
In the Byzantine generals problem,
我们假定消息传输可靠 但节点可能是不诚实的
we assumed that messages are reliable, but nodes might be dishonest.
现在 我们会把两种情况放到一起
So now, well, we should put the two together really,
尝试为系统设计系统模型
and try and design system models for system
模型允许节点和网络可能存在各种不同的错误情况
in which both nodes and networks might go wrong in various ways.
系统模型是分布式系统中所有算法的基石
And so, this is really the foundation of any algorithms in distributed systems.
我们需要明确假设系统拥有哪些特性
We need to assume certain things about what properties the system is going to have.
一般来说 我们会考虑三个方向
And typically, we do that by looking at three different areas of interest.
第一 我们需要定义网络可能出现的情况
So, first of all, we need to describe how we assume the network is going to behave.
第二 我们需要定义节点可能出现的情况
Secondly, we're going to assume how nodes are going to behave.
第三 我们需要定义系统中的时间情况
And thirdly, we need to assume how the timing in the system is going to work.
时间会同时影响到网络和节点
So, the timing affects both networks and nodes.
这是系统模型所需要描述的三个方面
So, those are the three aspects of a system model
在本节中 我们将分别介绍这三方面的内容
that we're going to look at now in this section.
我们先从网络开始
Let's start with networks.
我已经重复强调了很多次 网络是不可靠的
So, I've repeated over and over again that networks are unreliable,
但我需要再次强调
but just to re-emphasize that
消息可能由于各种各样的原因在网络中丢失
there are many reasons why message might get lost in a network.
有些时候 消息丢失可能只是因为网络临时超载
Some of them are just temporary overload.
缓存区已经满了 一条消息因此被舍弃了
A buffer gets full, and so a message gets dropped.
即使你小心谨慎地设计系统 使缓存区永远不会溢出
But also, there are some more fundamental problems,
系统仍然会面临很多基础问题
even if you design it carefully so that your buffers never overflow.
有些负责运行系统的人可能会插错网线
Some human operating a system might just unplug the wrong network cable.
当网线插错了的时候 网络肯定会中断一段时间
And that means the network will be interrupted for the time
我们不能回避这类问题
that this network cable is unplugged. No way around it.
还有很多因自然环境导致网络中断的奇奇怪怪的原因
There are also various other curious interactions with nature that happen.
举例来说 谷歌观察到
So, Google was observing, for example,
它们的海底光缆出现了莫名其妙的损坏情况
on their subsea fiber optic cables that they were strange damaged.
它们观察到光缆上有奇怪的损坏痕迹
They observed strange damage on these cables.
它们安装了一些海底摄像头
And they installed some underwater cameras
结果观察到鲨鱼在咬光缆
and actually managed to observe sharks biting into their cables.
你可以看看幻灯片中链接的视频
You can see the video at the link here on the slide.
力荐此视频 特别好玩
Do watch it. It's incredibly cute.
在陆地上 人们也可能观察到奶牛踩踏光纤等问题
On land, people have observed problems with cows stepping on fiber optic cables.
光纤一般会沿着电力线部署
So, a fiber optic cable was supposed to run along a power line,
但最后总要落回到地表上
but ended up trailing on the ground.
奶牛踩了上去 奶牛的踩踏动作使光纤出现严重扭曲
Cow steps on it, and the cow makes enough of a kink in the cable
光无法在严重扭曲的光纤中传播
that the light can't get through the kink in the fiber optic cable,
因此 网络连接出现了中断
and thus, the network link gets interrupted.
确实有可能发生这类情况
This stuff really happens honestly.
网络可能因为多种多样的原因出现故障
So, lots of reasons why networks might fail.
我们把这些故障往上抽象一层
Let's take this to a bit more abstract level
以便我们可以更形式化地描述可能出现的故障
so that we can reason about it in a more formal way.
在分布式系统中 当我们设计分布式算法时
So, typically in distributed systems, and when we're designing distributed algorithms,
我们一般假定节点之间是点对点通信的
we are going to assume some kind of point-to-point communication.
我们假定消息有一个发送方和一个接收方
So, we're going to assume that messages have one sender and one recipient.
他们通过双向链路发送数据
And they are sent over a bi-directional link
这使得接收方可以向发送方回复响应
so that the recipient can then reply back to the sender.
不管我们前面讨论的链路具体是如何构建的 我们都把它抽象成这种形式
So, that's everything the type of link we've been talking about so far.
我们可以进一步假设链路的可靠程度
And we can then choose how reliable we are going to assume this link is.
最简单的可靠程度假设模型是
And so, the simplest model to program against is
我们简单地假设链路是可靠的
if we simply assume that the link is reliable,
也就是说 消息总能够被成功传输
and that is, that messages always get through.
当发送一条消息时 这条消息一定能被接收到
If a message is sent, then it is received.
如果接收到一条消息 那这条消息一定是前面发送的消息
And if a message is received, then it was previously sent.
链路不会丢失消息
So, the link doesn't lose messages,
链路也不会平白无故地制造消息
and the link also doesn't fabricate messages out of thin air.
接收的消息一定是之前发送的消息
So, a message is only received if it was sent.
但我们会假设消息的顺序可能会被打乱
But we're going to assume that messages can be reordered.
这当然是一个非常强的链路假设
And so, that is quite a strong assumption, of course,
因为实际中的链路不可能做到如此可靠
because links may not actually be this reliable in practice.
我们后面就会介绍如何获得可靠链路
But we'll get to that in a moment.
我们会为链路设定的第二个假设是
The second assumption we could make about network links is
公平丢包链路
what is called a fair-loss link.
公平丢包链路是指
So, a fair-loss link is one in which
当你发送一条消息时 消息会有非零的概率传输成功
whenever you send a message, it has a non-zero probability of being delivered.
当你发送一条消息时 这条消息可能会被发送到 也可能不会被发送到
So, when you send a message, it might get through, it might not get through.
但如果你持续重复地发送这条消息
But if you keep repeating the sending of that message,
那么我们可以假定此消息最终一定能被成功传输
then we're going to assume that eventually it will get through.
我们不会假设消息需要花费多长时间才能被成功传输
We're not going to make any assumptions about how long that might take.
消息可能要花费相当长的时间才能被成功传输
So, it might take a long time until the message does finally get through.
但我们会假设 如果你的服务执行时间为无穷长
But we're going to assume that if you assume an infinitely long execution time,
那么在有限长时间内的某个时刻
there will at some point within a finite amount of time be a point
所有消息都会被成功传输
when every message is delivered.
我们对网络链路能设定的第三个 也是最弱的假设是任意网络
And the third, the weakest assumption we could make about network links is arbitrary.
我们允许此类网络链路发生任何事情
So, the network link is allowed to do anything.
我们可以将此链路建模为
We can model this
存在一个恶意的主动攻击者 他可以修改网络流量
in terms of a malicious active adversary who modifies the network traffic.
在真实的互联网中 确实存在这样的链路
And so, this actually does happen on the real Internet.
如果你连接到咖啡店的Wi-Fi 则此Wi-Fi的拥有者
If you're connecting to a coffee shop Wi-Fi, the owner of that Wi-Fi
可能会用任何方式干扰你发送的网络数据包
could be interfering with your network packets in arbitrary ways,
也就是说 他们不仅会查看你的网络通信内容
and that means they might not just be looking at your network communication,
即监听网络流
like eavesdropping on it,
他们甚至可能会修改数据包
but they might actually modify the packets.
他们可能会记录数据包 在后续的某个时间内重放此数据包
They might record packets, and then replay them at some later point of time.
他们可能会伪装成某个网站 实施仿冒攻击
They might pretend to be some website and spoof it.
当然了 他们也可能会丢弃你发送的消息
And of course, they might drop messages as well.
我们允许任意链路发生任何可能发生的事情
And so, an arbitrary link is allowed to do any of these things.
很不幸 用这一链路模型描述正在使用的互联网才是合理的
And unfortunately, this is actually a reasonable model of how the Internet works today.
我想介绍的最后一个术语和概念是
Now, a final piece of terminology that I want to introduce here
网络分区
is the concept of a network partition.
网络分区是指 你有一些节点
So, network partition is just if you have some nodes
这些节点仍然可以持续运行
where the nodes are still continuing to run fine,
但节点间的通信链路可能会被中断
but the communication link between them is interrupted.
一般来说 我们认为网络会在有限的时间内发生中断
Usually, we talk about this interruption of being for some finite period of time.
也就是说 网络分区最终总能被修复
So, eventually, the network partition does get repaired.
在未来的某个时刻 节点间又可以重新进行通信了
And at some point in the future, they will be able to communicate again.
但中断周期可能会非常长
But the period of interruption might be quite substantial.
这是一个非常重要的概念 请大家牢记
And this is an important thing to keep in mind.
举例来说 你可能有一个系统
So, you might have systems, for example,
系统中的一个节点子群允许相互通信
where one subgroup of nodes is able to communicate,
系统中的另一个节点子群也允许相互通信
a different subgroup of nodes is able to communicate,
但这两个子群之间无法相互通信
but those two groups cannot communicate between them,
因为这两个子群之间的网络链路发生了中断
because the network link between the two groups is interrupted.
这种情况是绝对有可能会发生的
So, this could absolutely happen.
围绕这三个网络行为模型 有一个非常有趣的结论
So now, the interesting thing with the three models of network behavior is that
总能将一个网络模型转换为另一个网络模型
it's actually almost possible to convert one model into another.
特别地 如果我们有一个公平丢包链路
So, in particular, if we have a fair-loss link,
我们可以把这个公平丢包链路转换为可靠链路
we can turn a fair-loss link into a reliable link.
实现转换的方法非常简单 只需要一直重试发送消息 直到消息被成功传输
And the way we can do that is we simply keep retrying messages until they get through.
这也意味着接收方侧会收到重复消息
And on the recipient side, that means we might get duplicate messages.
因此 我们需要在接收方侧对消息进行去重处理
So, we have to also deduplicate the messages on the recipient side.
因为我们在公平丢包链路中假设
And because with a fair-loss link, we are assuming that
如果我们一直重试 消息最终都能被成功传输
if we keep retrying, a message will eventually get through,
因此 总可以将公平丢包链路转换为可靠链路
then it is actually possible to turn this into a reliable link
因为我们假定消息最终一定能被成功传输
because we're assuming it will eventually get through
因此 只要一直重试 消息就一定能被成功传输
and therefore, by keep retrying, it will eventually get through.
当然了 我们没有明确这要花费多长的时间
Of course, we're not saying anything about how long that is going to take.
消息被成功传输所花费的时间可能会非常长
It could potentially take a very long time for a message to get through,
但最终总能被成功传输
but it will eventually get through.
有趣的是 一般情况下 总能将一个任意链路转换为一个公平丢包链路
Interestingly, it's also almost possible to convert an arbitrary link into a fair-loss link.
实现此转换的方法是使用类似TLS的密码学协议
And the way we can do that is by using a cryptographic protocol such as TLS.
TLS表示传输层安全协议
So, TLS, which stands for Transport Layer Security,
它为你的浏览器带来了一个小绿锁
is what gives you the little green padlock in the browser,
它为你的HTTP协议带来了额外的字母S
it's what gives you the S in HTTPS.
这是一个安全协议 允许客户端和服务端之间实现通信
So, it's a security protocol that allows typically a client and a server to communicate
且保证通信链路可以抵抗网络流中发生的人为干扰
in a way that is resilient to people interfering with the network traffic.
也就是说 即使网络中存在主动攻击者
So, even if there's some active adversary on the network
他可以操纵你的网络通信链路
who is manipulating your network communication,
TLS协议有能力保证
the TLS protocol is able to guarantee that
只要通信成功 则通信的消息就不会被篡改
if the communication is successful, then it hasn't been tampered with.
这是一个认证通信链路 可以抵御仿冒攻击
And it is authentic communication. It hasn't been spoofed.
当你想和网站通信时
You don't have some other person
其他人无法伪装成这个网站和你通信
impersonating the website you're trying to communicate with, and so on.
因为数据经过了加密 因此通信链路也是私密的
And the communication is private, because it's encrypted.
通过使用TLS这类协议
And so, by using a protocol like TLS,
我们实际上有能力将任意链路转换为公平丢包链路
we're actually able to almost change an arbitrary link into a fair-loss link.
我们唯一无法做到是
The only thing we cannot do is
如果主动攻击者直接决定阻断所有的通信链路 那我们就无能为力了
if the active adversary just decides to block all communication ever.
很显然 在这种情况下 任何消息都不可能被成功传输
In that case, of course, nothing is going to get through.
我们也无法将这种任意链路转换为公平丢包链路
And you can't turn that into a fair-loss link,
因为我们无法保证
because we can't make any guarantee that
如果持续重试 消息就一定能被成功传输
eventually a message will get through if you keep retrying.
但如果我们可以假设
But if we're willing to assume that
攻击者只会干扰有限数量的数据包
the adversary will only interfere, say, with a finite number of packets,
那我们就可以称
then we could say that,
可以将任意链路升级为公平丢包链路
OK, the arbitrary link can be actually upgraded to a fair-loss link,
而通过持续重试和数据包去重
and from there, through retrying and deduplication,
我们可以进一步把链路转换为可靠链路
we can actually turn it into a reliable link.
这就是我们的网络行为模型
So, that's our model of network behavior.
系统模型的下一部分是 如何为节点行为建模
The next part of the system model is how the nodes behave.
很显然 节点也有很多不同类型的故障
So, of course, nodes might fail in various ways as well.
我们考虑的第一种故障是崩溃故障
And the first type of fault that we want to consider here is a crash fault.
我们将此类进程故障抽象为崩溃停止 崩溃停止的意思是
And so, in the crash-stop abstraction for a process, what this means is that
我们假设进程在某个时刻崩溃了
we assume that a process might crash at any moment.
一旦进程崩溃
And once a process has crashed,
它将再也无法恢复 永远处于死机状态
then it will never come back again, it's just dead forever.
节点一旦崩溃便永远死机 这很显然是一种非常简化的假设
So, this is a simplifying assumption, of course, that it's going to be dead forever.
在某些情况下 这种故障定义是准确的
In some cases, this is accurate.
如果你的节点是你的手机
So, if your node is your phone,
你一没留神 手机掉到了马桶里面 手机因此彻底损坏了
and you drop your phone in the toilet, and the phone is there after broken,
手机相当于突然从这个世界上消失了
the phone has suddenly disappeared off the face of the earth,
它再也修不好了
and it's never going to come back again,
我们再也无法与这台手机通信了
it's never going to be able to communicate again.
你可以把这种情况建模为崩溃停止故障
So, therefore, you can model this as a crash stop failure.
也就是说 崩溃指的并不一定是软件崩溃
So, the crash might not just be a software crash.
也可以是灾难性的硬件崩溃
It could also be a catastrophic hardware failure,
节点有可能被破坏 再也无法恢复了
where a node is simply destroyed, and it will never be able to come back again.
但在其他系统中 我们一般会假设
But in other systems, we might want to assume actually that
节点可能会崩溃 但后面还能恢复
nodes might crash and then come back again.
经过某个时间阶段后 节点可能会恢复
They might recover after some period of time.
当一个节点崩溃时 我们一般会假设
When a node crashes, we probably want to assume that
节点的所有内存状态都会丢失
any in-memory state that it had is lost.
任何未写入硬盘或其他非易失存储设备的状态都会丢失
So, any state that is not written to disk or to other some non-volatile storage will be lost.
但所有已经写入稳态存储器的数据都可以在崩溃中存活下来
But any data that is stored in stable storage is able to survive the crash,
当节点恢复时 这些数据也能得到恢复
and will be there after the node recovers.
当然了 崩溃恢复模型中的节点也有可能崩溃后再也无法恢复
Of course, crash-recovery model nodes might still crash and never come back again.
这种概率也是存在的
So, that's still a possibility.
我们只是增加了一种可能性：节点崩溃后还有可能恢复
We're just adding the additional possibility that the node might recover after our crash.
第三个节点模型是拜占庭模型
And the third model of nodes is Byzantine,
这里的“拜占庭”就是拜占庭将军问题中的“拜占庭”
so, exactly as in the Byzantine generals problem.
拜占庭故障节点的意思是 节点可能会偏离其需要执行的算法
What it means for a node to be Byzantine faulty is just it deviates from the algorithm.
我们假定节点会遵从算法的执行流程
So, we specify an algorithm that all of the nodes are supposed to follow,
但拜占庭故障节点可能不会遵从算法的执行流程
but a Byzantine faulty node may not follow the algorithm.
它可能会假装遵从算法的执行流程
It might pretend to follow the algorithm.
它可能会让自己看起来像一个诚实节点
It might do stuff to try and make it look honest,
但它有可能实际上在执行恶意行为
even though it's actually behaving in some malicious way.
我们不会对拜占庭故障节点的行为做出任何限制
So, we're not going to constrain the behavior of a Byzantine faulty node in any way.
我们只是假设
We're just going to assume that
此类节点可能会做出包括恶意行为在内的任何行为
it can do anything that it wants, including malicious behavior.
这里还涉及到一个术语
And so, a piece of terminology here is
我们总可以把节点分类为故障节点和正确节点
we can always categorize a node as either faulty or correct.
例如 如果节点崩溃了 那它就属于故障节点
So, a node is faulty if it crashes, for example,
或者在拜占庭模型中 如果节点偏离了算法 那它就属于故障节点
or in the Byzantine model, a node is faulty if it deviates from the algorithm.
如果节点没有发生故障 那它就属于正确节点
A node is correct if it's not faulty.
总之 节点有这两种可能的状态
So, those are the two possibilities.
一个节点可以不必知道另一个节点是正确节点还是故障节点
Now, one node does not necessarily know whether another node is correct or faulty.
我们稍后会介绍实现故障检查所需面对的问题
And we will come to the problem of fault detection in a little while.
我们已经讨论了网络模型和节点模型
So, we've talked about models for network, models for nodes.
第三部分是为时间模型
The third part is models for timing.
同样地 我们有三种可以选择的模型
And so, here again, they are one of three choices that we could make.
我们的第一个选择是同步系统模型
So, the first choice we could make is a synchronous system model.
在同步系统模型中 我们假设
And in a synchronous system model, we assume that
所有活动发生的时长都是已知的
basically everything takes a known length of time.
当我们通过网络发送一条消息时
So, when we send a message over the network,
消息传递成功或失败有一个最大时长
there is some maximum time after which the message will be either delivered or lost,
我们假设
but we assume that
任何消息到达的时间都不会超过最大时长
no message will take longer than some maximum amount of time to arrive.
我们同样假设 节点总会按照已知的速度执行代码
Also, we're going to assume that nodes always execute their code at a known speed.
对于每一步执行流程 对于每一步算法
So, every step of execution, every step of the algorithm,
节点执行的时长都存在一个上界
there's an upper bound for the length of time that that execution is going to take.
这是一个很强的假设
This is a very strong assumption.
我们可以做出的另一个假设是部分同步模型
Now, another assumption we could make is a partially synchronous model,
在一段时间周期内 系统的行为满足同步模型的定义
where for some periods of time, the system behaves as in the synchronous model,
在另一段时间周期内 系统的行为是异步的
and for other periods of time, it behaves in a way that's asynchronous.
我需要解释一下什么叫做异步
And so, I need to explain asynchronous.
在异步模型中 我们不对时间做出任何假设
So, in an asynchronous model, we make no timing assumptions at all.
这意味着 如果我们通过网络发送一条消息
So, that means if you send a message over the network,
此消息可能花了20年才传输成功
it may arrive in 20 years' time, OK?
我们不保证
We're not making any guarantees about
消息需要花费多长时间才能到达目的地
how long it's going to take for messages to arrive.
我们不假设消息延迟时长存在上界
We assume no upper bound on message latency.
当然了 大多数消息可能很快就会被成功传输
Of course, it might be that messages are mostly delivered quite quickly,
但我们不会假设
but we're just not going to make any assumptions about
消息传输存在某个时延上界
the maximum latency that might occur.
进一步 我们不会假设
Moreover, we're not going to make any assumptions about
节点会以多快的速度执行算法
how fast nodes are going to execute the algorithm.
我们假设节点可能会在任何时刻暂停执行
So, we're going to assume that a node might pause its execution at any moment,
节点会在一段时间内停止执行算法 随后又会恢复执行
and just like stop executing its steps for a while, and then later resume executing again.
这当然是有可能发生的 大家也知道 线程有可能会被挂起
And of course, this can happen, because a thread can be suspended as you know.
线程可能会暂停执行一段时间
And so, a thread can just pause execution for a while,
随后再恢复执行
and then resume executing sometime later.
我们定义了同步模型这种极端情况
And so, we have here the synchronous model as one extreme
在这种极端情况下 我们对网络延迟和节点处理速度
where like we're making very strong assumptions about
设置了一个很强的假设
the network latency and the node processing speed,
而在异步模型中 我们没有设置任何假设
and the asynchronous model where we're making no assumptions at all.
部分同步模型是这两种极端情况的折中情况
So, the partially synchronous model is kind of a compromise between those two,
我们一般认为
where we're saying that actually
系统最好能支持异步模型
the asynchronous model is great if we can work in the asynchronous model,
但确实有一些特定的问题无法在异步模型中解决
but there are certain problems that simply cannot be solved in the asynchronous model.
在某些情况下 我们不得不对时间做出一些假设
So, in some cases, we do have to make timing assumptions.
但于此同时 我们不能简单的认为
But at the same time, it's unsafe to assume that
设置的时间假设总是成立的
those timing assumptions are always true,
如果你在同步模型下写出了一个算法
because if you write an algorithm in the synchronous model,
但系统实际上是异步的
and the system is ever asynchronous,
举例来说 如果系统传递消息的时间超过了你假设的时延上界
if the system ever takes longer than your upper bound to deliver a message, for example,
那你的算法可能会灾难性地失败
then your algorithm might fail catastrophically.
同步模型下的算法可能会对时间假设异常敏感
So, the algorithms are very very sensitive to your timing assumptions here.
在大多数情况下 假设系统满足同步模型是非常危险的
And in most cases, it is very dangerous to assume a synchronous model,
因为现实世界中的网络行为与部分同步模型假设有些类似
because real networks do in fact behave in partially synchronous ways.
部分同步模型假设是一个折中假设
So, partially synchronous model is really our compromise
在部分同步模型中 我们认为系统行为在大多数情况下都是同步的
where we're saying most of the time the system is well behaved and kind of synchronous,
但系统偶尔会出现奇怪的情况
and occasionally it just goes weird,
消息偶尔会花费很长的时间才能传输成功
and occasionally messages take a really long time to arrive,
节点的执行速度偶尔会变得特别慢
and occasionally nodes are really slow to execute.
随后 在某个时刻 系统又会返回到同步状态
And then, at some point, they'll return back into a synchronous state,
但我们不知道当前系统到底处于同步状态还是异步状态
but we don't know whether they're asynchronous or synchronous right now.
让我来解释一下直接假设同步模型会遇到的问题
So, let me just explain the problems of assuming synchrony.
你可能会认为 大多数时间内的网络传输都是很流畅的
So, you might think that, you know, usually networks are quite fast,
一般来说 发送的一条消息很快就能传输成功
and usually if you send a message, then it'll be arrived,
到达时间一般都不会超过某个最长时间
it'll arrive within some maximum time.
但很不幸的是
But unfortunately,
有很多原因会导致消息偶尔会出现很长的传输时延
there are lots of reasons why messages might take longer occasionally.
第一个可能的原因是 消息就是丢失了 需要重试
And so, one reason might be that a message is lost and needs to be retried.
我前面也提到 在公平丢包链路升级为可靠链路的场景下
And so, like we had earlier, in our case of upgrading a fair-loss link to a reliable link,
升级为可靠链路的主要开销来自于
the cost of that upgrade in reliability was that
有时我们可能需要等待很长的时间才能发送出消息
potentially we have to wait for a very long time.
如果存在网络分区
If there's a network partition,
可能需要等待几分钟、几个小时、甚至几天的时间
we might have to wait for minutes, or even hours, or even days
消息才能传输成功
before the message gets through.
在这种情况下 我们不能假设消息传输有一个最大延时上界
So, in this case, we can't assume any upper bound really on message latency,
因为延时可能会等于网络分区的修复时长
because it might be up to the length that it takes for our network partition to be healed.
网络延迟突然变高的另一个原因
Other reasons why network latency might suddenly increase
也可能是网络发生了阻塞和排队的情况
is just congestion and queuing in the network,
还可能发生的一个例子是网络配置发生了修改
or there have even been examples of a network reconfiguration
这使得数据包在交换缓存区中卡了几分钟后
where packets just get stuck in a switch buffer for over a minute
才能被传输出去
before they're eventually delivered.
因此 即使在数据中心网络这种管理有方的网络场景
And so, even in data center networks which are normally very well-managed,
也可能会偶发性地出现极高的消息传输延迟
it is possible to actually occasionally have really extremely high message latency.
因此 我们设计的任何算法都需要考虑
And so, any algorithm that we design must take into account this possibility that
出现偶发性超高消息传输延迟的可能性
occasionally messages might take a very long time to arrive.
对于节点执行速度 我们一般会期望
In terms of the execution speed of nodes, again, we would expect normally like
计算机会按照固定的时钟速率下执行算法
computers run at a kind of fixed speed, a fixed clock speed.
但我们不能认为执行速率就会变得非常非常稳定
So, we don't expect that to very very much.
有很多原因会导致
But there are many reasons
节点执行过程中出现偶发性中断
why a node's execution might be interrupted for a little while.
大家在本课程的并发系统部分已经学过
So, as you know from the concurrent systems part of this course,
系统实现可能包含上下文切换
you can have a context switch,
你的某个线程可能会被临时挂起 而其他进程还在正常运行
you can have a thread that temporarily gets suspended while other processes run.
可能要等待一段时间
And so, this might take a while
操作系统的调度算法才能回过头来再次启动你的线程
before the operating system scheduler comes back and starts running your thread again,
尤其是当系统出现一些问题时 例如系统发生了优先级倒置
Especially if there's some kind of problem going on, like priority inversion in the system,
此时 进程可能会出现长时间的暂停
it could be that a process is actually paused for a significant amount of time
随后才能重新运行起来
before it gets to run again.
在多线程下
And as you know from multi-threading,
进程或线程可能会在任何时刻暂停
a process can or a thread can get paused that absolutely any moment.
代码中的任何位置都有可能遇到暂停情况
There's any point in the code it could decide to pause.
即使在算法最不适合暂停的地方
And so, even at the most inconvenient place possible in an algorithm,
也可能会发生线程暂停或上下文切换
you might have a thread pause or a context switch.
在实际中可能发生的另一个问题是垃圾回收
Another real problem that happens in practice is garbage collection,
举个例子 Java这样的语言
so, in a language like Java, for example,
会执行自动化内存管理
which performs automatic memory management,
它会使用垃圾回收机制释放内存
and which uses garbage collection to free up memory,
你可能会遇到所谓的“停止一切”垃圾回收暂停机制
you can have what is called a “stop-the-world” garbage collection pause,
垃圾回收器会让所有正在运行的线程停止一段时间
where the garbage collector just has to stop all of the running threads for a while,
执行垃圾回收
while it performs the garbage collection.
如果你的堆空间很大 则暂停时间有时甚至会达到分钟级
And those pauses can last minutes sometimes if you have a large heap size.
这是进程或线程
So, that again is another reason
可能会暂停执行一段时间的另一个原因
why a process or a thread might just pause execution for a while.
最后 操作系统当然也可能出现很多意想不到的情况
And finally, of course, there are lots of other things in the operating system
分页错误等都有可能导致不可预知的处理延迟
that cause variable delays, such as page faults and so on,
内存空间受限时尤其可能出现延迟
especially if memory is tight.
确实有可能避免操作系统出现上述情况
So, it is possible to get around these things.
实时操作系统会提供调度保证机制
So, real-time operating systems will provide scheduling guarantees.
实时操作系统会保证每行代码的执行时间间隔不会超过10毫秒
They might guarantee that your code always runs at least once every 10 milliseconds.
但大多数分布式系统不是基于实时操作系统构建的
But most distributed systems are not built on real-time operating systems.
它们一般都构建在通用操作系统上
They're built on general purpose operating systems,
通用操作系统不能为进程调度提供任何时延保证
which make no guarantees about how processes are going to get scheduled.
即使你使用的就是实时操作系统
And even if you are using a real-time operating system,
也很难保证时间调度机制永远满足时间要求
it's very hard work to actually ensure that those timing guarantees always hold.
对于大多数实际场景下的分布式系统来说
So, for most practical distributed systems,
我们无法对时长设置任何上界
we cannot assume any upper bound on how long it might take
这里的时长包括消息传递时长和进程单步执行时长
for both a message to be delivered, or a process to execute one step,
因为在任何时刻下 延迟的发生都是不确定的 也是不可预测的
because these delays can occur unpredictably and non-deterministically at any point.
我们对这部分介绍的内容做个总结
So, that's a summary. This is what we talked about.
系统模型包含三个部分
System model consists of three parts.
我们可以假设网络的可靠性
We can make an assumption about the network,
假设网络是可靠的、公平丢包的、还是任意的
how reliable we want the network to be reliable, fair-loss or arbitrary.
我们可以假设节点可能的行为
We make an assumption about how nodes are going to behave.
我们可以假设崩溃停止节点 意思是节点一旦崩溃就再也无法恢复了
So, are we going to assume crash-stop, where crash means a node never comes back,
也可以假设崩溃恢复节点 甚至假设拜占庭节点
or crash-recovery, or even Byzantine behavior of nodes.
第三部分是时间模型
And then, thirdly for the timing, we can choose
我们可以选择同步执行、部分同步执行、以及异步执行
between synchronous or partially synchronous or asynchronous execution.
这些抽象模型的选择结果对分布式系统来说非常重要
And these choices of abstraction are absolutely crucial.
如果你在设计一个分布式系统
So, if you're designing a distributed algorithm,
你必须非常确定你所选择的假设是否正确
you have to be absolutely certain that your assumption in regard to these are correct.
举例来说 如果你假设崩溃恢复模型
So, for example, if you're assuming a crash-recovery model
但实际上 你的系统中存在一些拜占庭节点
and actually, you have some Byzantine nodes in your system,
拜占庭节点就会毁掉你的算法
the Byzantine nodes are just going to destroy your algorithm.
如果你认为节点可能存在拜占庭行为
So, if you think they're going to be Byzantine behavior,
你就需要在算法设计中考虑到相应的情况
then you have to take account for it in the algorithm,
所设计的算法需要容忍拜占庭行为
and the algorithm has to be designed to tolerate Byzantine behavior.
直接假设系统满足较高的假设要求也没什么问题
It is perfectly fine if you're going to assume
你可以假设这是一个全可信系统 没有任何拜占庭节点
this is a fully trusted system, it's not going to have any Byzantine nodes,
可以假设只存在崩溃停止节点和崩溃恢复节点
and just assume only crash-stop or crash-recovery.
这么假设也没问题 只是必须确定你所选择的假设是正确的
That's fine. You just have to be very sure that your assumption is correct.
时间假设也一样
Likewise, with timing,
我前面提到 假设同步模型 但系统实际上仅满足部分同步模型
making synchrony assumptions, as I said, assuming a synchronous model
这种情况是非常危险的
when actually your system is partially synchronous is very dangerous.
如果你假设的是同步模型
It's very likely that if you assume a synchronous model,
哪怕系统只有10秒钟的时间处于部分同步状态
and it goes partially synchronous even just for like 10 seconds somewhere,
你设计的分布式算法都有可能无法工作
all of the guarantees of your distributed algorithm are off.
你必须非常确定你所选择的假设是否正确
So, you have to be very sure that your assumptions
要正确选择时间模型、节点行为模型、以及网络模型
in terms of the synchrony model, the node behavior, and the network are correct.